Richard Wilson Papers
Richard Wilson Papers
- Printed material
  - Fanzines
    - Lobster Tails, [1980]; no. 8, no. 9 (Box 11)
    - Mae Strelkov Trip Report, 1976 (Box 11)
    - Maya, 1975; no. 7 (Box 11)
    - Nucleus, [1977?]; vol. 1 no. 1, 2, 3 (Box 11)
    - Science Fiction Forum, 1957; vol. 1 no. 1, 2 (Box 11)
    - Science Fiction Newsletter, 1937-1938; vol. 1 no. 1-26; vol. 2 no. 1-26 (Box 11)
    - Science Fiction Review, 1982; no. 43 (Box 11)
    - Shangri L'Affaires, 1946-1947; no. 32, no. 35 (Box 11)
    - SFS Refractions, 1982; 3 issues (Box 11)
    - The Skylee Sun, 1971; no. 1 (Box 11)
    - Synapse, [1969-1970?]; 3 issues (Box 11)
    - Tink; Tong; Tunkunaku Event, 1973-1974; three different titles, all by Mae Strelkov (Box 13)
    - The Vinegar Worm, 1967; vol. 2 no. 10 (reprint) (Box 11)
    - The Vombus [?], 1937; incomplete; editors listed as James V. Taurasi and Richard Wilson; possibly related to Voice of the Imagination, known as VOM (Box 11)
  - Newsletters
    - First Fandom, 1968; 1971; published by First Fandom; no. 1, 2, 5; also includes First Fandom Magazine no. 15 (Box 11)
    - The Realist, 1963-1966; published by The Realist Association; no. 44-46, 50, 54, 60, 63, 64, 73, 86; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Renaissance, 1970; published by the Second Foundation; vol. 2 no. 4 (Box 13)
  - Publishers
    - Miscellaneous, Borgo Press, Gregg Science Fiction, Hyperion, Pocket, Pulp Press, more; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
- Subject files
  - 339th Fighter Squadron/347th Fighter Group, 1944-1945; miscellaneous material (Box 13)
    This material is closed to researchers pending review.
  - 347th Fighter Group, 1943-1945; lists of achievements; AR 345-105 reports; award recommendations, narrative history, press releases, roster and casualty lists,; 7 folders (Box 13)
  - 347th Fighter Group, 1943-1945; miscellaneous official documents; personal accounts; 2 folders (Box 14)
  - FBI, 1949-1950 (Box 14)
  - Flying saucers / UFOs, 1947-1973; undated; clippings; 5 folders (Box 14)
  - Flying saucers / UFOs, 1947; 1950,; 1967-1968; magazines, including a comic book; 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Pohl, Frederik, 1945; 1966-1968; clippings, correspondence about, etc. (Box 14)
  - Reuter's
    - Commemorative items, 1950; 1962 (Box 14)
    - Official communications, 1953-1956 (Box 14)
    - Style notes, 1951 (Box 14)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - Aunt Fritzi, 1986; clipping of published article about Fritzi Kelly, Wilson's aunt (Box 15)
    - Albert Finney, 1964; drafts, letter to Movie Times accompanying submission (Box 15)
    - Flying saucer series, 1950; drafts; first article is by Wilson, others are by Douglas Grahame, Dan Edelstein, Cyril Kornbluth, Wallace R. Fanning; includes a few items of correspondence with Fanning (Box 15)
    - Invasion of the Beatles, 1964; notes, drafts, research material (Box 15)
    - Military, miscellaneous, 1944-1946; drafts and clippings of published items, including some in Wilson's high school magazine The Dome (Box 15)
    - Reuters, miscellaneous, 1943; 1952,; 1958-1961; drafts, final submitted copy (Box 15)
    - Tops in Pops column, 1951; written while Wilson was at Transradio Press; drafts and tear-sheets or clippings of published columns from The Daily Gazette (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous, 1948; 1953,; 1983 (Box 15)
  - Books
    Both novels and novellas are filed here, including seven folders of material for Wilson's Nebula Award-winning novelette "Mother to the World."
    - At the sign of the Boar's Head Nebula [working title: Saffron]
      - Notes, foldered, 4 folders (Box 15)
      - Notes, miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - "Old carbons, early drafts, shorter version" (Box 16)
      - Early drafts, 6 folders (Box 16)
      - Draft, 1966 (Box 16)
      - "30,000 word version", 1969; 3 folders (Box 16)
      - "Original copy", 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Final[?] draft (Box 17)
      - "Finished copy", appears to actually be partial drafts; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - The far king
      - "Working folder" (Box 17)
      - Early draft, handwritten (Box 17)
      - "Pre-July 1976 ms" (Box 17)
      - Typescript (Box 17)
      - "Penultimate draft" (Box 18)
      - Final draft (Box 18)
      - Setting copy (Box 18)
      - Proofs / galleys (Box 18)
    - The girls from Planet 5
      - Final, incomplete, contains pp. 65-251; 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Published editions, 1955; 1957,; 1962; Ballantine hardcover, 1955, signed; Ballantine paperback, 1957, signed; Hachette, 1962 (Le Rayon Fantastique 92), signed (Box 18)
      - Musical comedy version outline (Box 18)
    - I thought I heard him play
      - Synopsis (Box 18)
      - Notes, 3 folders (Box 18)
      - Draft, 4 folders (Box 19)
    - The kid from Ozone Park
      - Published edition, Drumm booklet #27, 1987 (Box 19)
    - The 19th century spaceship
      - Drafts and notes, 3 folders (Box 19)
      - Final draft, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Super city
      See also Miscellaneous: "First drafts incorporated in published works".
      - Notes, miscellaneous pages, corrections (Box 19)
      - Draft, pp. 1-75 (Box 19)
      - Draft, pp. 76-149 (Box 20)
    - 30 day wonder
      - Notes (Box 20)
      - Quotes for chapter headings (Box 20)
      - Draft, mostly handwritten, 7 folders (Box 20)
      - Final manuscript, pp. 1-150, 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Final manuscript, pp. 151-233 (Box 21)
      - Printer's copy, 3 folders (Box 21)
      - German edition, Utopia zukunfts roman #373 (Box 21)
    - Those idiots from Earth
      - Published edition, Ballantine paperback, 1957 (Box 21)
    - Time out for tomorrow [collection]
      - Published edition, Ballantine, 1962 (Box 21)
  - Plays
    - Another time, based on short story "Voice of the diaphragm"
      - Drafts, handwritten and typed (Box 21)
    - Jack and Jill
      - Course notes, Drama 135, 1964 (Box 21)
      - Outlines (Box 21)
      - Drafts A-D, 4 folders (Box 21)
      - Notes, fragments, miscellaneous revisions (Box 21)
      - Final (Box 22)
      - Submitted to WCAU "Repertoire Workshop", 1967 (Box 22)
  - Reviews
    - "Fantasy Stage and Screen" columns (Box 22)
    - Film, miscellaneous (Box 22)
    - Theater, miscellaneous (Box 22)
  - Stories
    Unless otherwise noted, material for a given story consists of handwritten and/or typed drafts.
    - An abundance of good things, 1953 (Box 22)
    - The archetype (Box 22)
    - The best possible world, 1959 (Box 22)
    - Beyond duty, pre-1944 (Box 22)
    - The big fix, 1953-1955 (Box 22)
    - Box, 1956-1963 (Box 22)
    - Boy, 1956 (Box 22)
    - The care and feeding of vampires (Box 22)
    - The Carson effect, 1959-1963 (Box 22)
    - Christmas party [alt title: Time out for tomorrow], 1953 (Box 22)
    - The day they had the war, 1965-1970 (Box 22)
    - Deny the slake, 1953-1956; 1970; notes, drafts, published version in Special Wonder Volume 2 (Box 22)
    - Deserter, 1955 (Box 22)
    - Don't fence me in, 1953; 1955 (Box 22)
    - The eight billion, 1956-1965; notes, research material, drafts, published version in Fantasy & Science Fiction; 3 folders (Box 22)
    - 88 beats 266, 1952 (Box 22)
    - The evil ones, notes, draft (Box 23)
    - Four star planet (Box 23)
    - Friend of the family, 1953 (Box 23)
    - Frostbite, 1951; 1956 (Box 23)
    - Gone past [alt title: Back from 1984], 1979-1980; notes, drafts, editor's manuscript; 4 folders (Box 23)
    - Grand prize, 1956 (Box 23)
    - Green eyes, 1957; 1969 (Box 23)
    - The hoaxters, 1952 (Box 23)
    - Honor, 1953 (Box 23)
    - The inhabited, 1952 (Box 23)
    - Inside story, 1953-1954 (Box 23)
    - It's cold outside, 1953; includes list of submissions (Box 23)
    - Just call me Irish (Box 23)
    - The largess in Manrun 2 [published as Kill me with kindness], 1957-1958; 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Lonely road, [1953?] (Box 23)
    - Love, 1951 (Box 23)
    - A man spekith [working title: Space disc jockey], 1967-1969; notes, research material, drafts; 6 folders (Box 24)
    - Man without a planet [alt. title: Willie] (Box 24)
    - Man working, 1957-1958 (Box 24)
    - The Martian princess, 1951 (Box 24)
    - The message (Box 24)
    - Mother to the world, notes, miscellaneous pages, drafts; 3 folders (Box 24)
    - Mother to the world, drafts, published version in Orbit; 4 folders (Box 25)
    - 9-9-99, 1967-1968 (Box 25)
    - Outside Earth (Box 25)
    - Press conference, 1952 (Box 25)
    - The purple boat [working title: The scientists' daughter] (Box 25)
    - QRM, 1956 (Box 25)
    - Revolt of the masses [alt title: The locus focus], 1956 (Box 25)
    - The rhyming invader, 1962; published version, in Kirmess (Box 25)
    - See me not, 1957; 3 folders (Box 25)
    - Soft hands, 1945 (Box 25)
    - The sons of Japheth, 1956 (Box 25)
    - The South Waterford Rumple Club, 1957-1968; notes, research material, drafts; 2 folders (Box 25)
    - The story writer, 1971-1972; 1978; notes, research material, drafts, typescript and cover letter submitted to Ace Books; 9 folders (Box 26)
    - Those idiots from Earth, 1957 (Box 26)
    - Transitory island (Box 26)
    - Tug hill, 1967; notes, research material (Box 26)
    - Tug hill, 1967; drafts; 4 folders (Box 27)
    - Tunnel under the world, 1951-1953 (Box 27)
    - Two very nice people, 1945 (Box 27)
    - The ubiquitous you [alt title: The in-betweens], 1952-1956 (Box 27)
    - The Venus papers, 1956-1957 (Box 27)
    - The voice of the diaphragm, 1956 (Box 27)
      See also Plays: Another time.
    - Wasp, 1953-1954 (Box 27)
    - The watchers in the glade, 1960-1963; 1967; notes, research material, drafts, published version in 9th Galaxy Reader; 4 folders (Box 27)
    - Wide open ship, galleys (Box 27)
    - You and eye (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous
    - "First drafts incorporated in published works" (Box 27)
    - George Pal interview, 1980; notes, research material, drafts (Box 27)
    - The singing handout, in College and University Journal, 1965 (Box 27)
    - Syracuse University's science fiction collections, 1966-1967; notes, drafts, etc.; includes galleys for published version in Worlds of Tomorrow (Box 27)
    - Trial notes, trials Wilson covered for Transradio Press
      - Coplon, Judith, 1949 (Box 28)
      - Gillars, Mildred (aka "Axis Sally"), 1949 (Box 28)
      - Klock, Bernard, 1952; 2 folders (Box 28)
      - Unidentified (Box 28)
    - Wilson fanzine, "Escape", 1939-1940; vol. 1, no's 3, 6, and 7 (Box 28)
  - By others
    - Blish, James, et al. / Criticism: Who needs it?, 1968; published by SFWA (Box 28)
    - Blish, James, et al. / Paranoia and science fiction, 1967; published by SFWA (Box 28)
    - Bloch, Robert / An index to Unknown and Unknown Worlds, 1955; published by Sirius Press (Box 28)
    - Bulmer, Kenneth / Dacre's last battle, writing as Nelson Sherwood; typescript draft with corrections; 2 folders (Box 28)
    - Bulmer, Kenneth / The fatal fire, typescript draft (Box 28)
    - Edelstein, Dan, See Articles: Flying saucer series.
    - Fanning, Wallace B., See Articles: Flying saucer series.
    - Grahame, Douglas, See Articles: Flying saucer series.
    - Kornbluth, Cyril, See Articles: Flying saucer series.
    - Lovecraft, H.P. / Notes on writing weird fiction, typescript draft (Box 28)
    - Pohl, Frederik, See also Articles: Flying saucer series.
    - Strauss, Erwin S. / The index to the S-F magazines, 1966-1967; self-published (Box 28)
    - Williamson, Jack / Science fiction comes to college, 1970-1971; raw material for report on college courses on SF (Box 28)
    - Unidentified (Box 28)